A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Developing Countries Program, Administrative Staff files FA556
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Developing Countries Program, Administrative Staff files
1960-1983
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA556
10.7 Cubic Feet
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs, became part of one International Division. A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program office. The collection spans from 1960-1983 and consists of administrative files of correspondence and memoranda between program officers in New York and overseas program representatives, narrative budget planning reports documenting grant making activities and goals, files relating to the work of consultants, and writings prepared for submission by the Foundation's representative in Japan.
Custodial History
The Developing Countries Program Administrative Staff collection consists of files maintained by Elisa Scatena and Richard W. Dye. Ms. Scatena, an administrative assistant for the Asia and Pacific Program based in New York, maintained files for the Asia office. As field offices closed or overseas representatives retired, the records were transferred to Ms. Scatena in New York. Mr. Dye was the Foundation Representative for the Andean Region and the Southern Cone. His files were transferred to the New York office after his retirement in 1981. The documents range in date from 1960 to 1983, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1970s. The files were transferred to the Archives in the mid-1980s.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation established the Overseas Development Program, one of its first grant programs, in 1951. Its granting goals were to increase agricultural production, improve health and living conditions, and advance education. India and Pakistan were the focus of the initial grants, with a more limited number of grants issued in Indonesia and Burma. A program for smaller regional and national grants was initiated for the Near East region later in the same year.
As part of a Foundation reorganization in 1966, the Overseas Development Program, along with other international Foundation programs such as International Training and Research and Population, became part of one International Division. A year later, in 1967, the South and Southeast Asia program was renamed Asia and the Pacific. A subsequent restructuring of the International Division occurred in 1980-1981 and led to the creation of the Developing Countries Program office. The Developing Countries Program was restructured in the 1989 Foundation reorganization.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 4 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Administrative Files, 1960-1983
Series II. Budgets, 1967-1974
Series III. Consultants, 1975-1981
Series IV. Writings, 1975-1976
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the activities of the Developing Countries Program in Latin America and Asia from 1960 to 1983. It consists of administrative files containing correspondence and memoranda between program officers in New York and overseas program representatives, as well as narrative budget planning reports documenting grant making activities and goals, files relating to the work of consultants, and writings prepared for submission by the Foundation's representative in Japan.
Administrative files, which constitute the bulk of the collection, contain information about a wide array of subjects. Subjects range from the general activities involved in running an overseas office such as program development, staffing, budgets, and office policies and procedures to relationships between overseas offices and their host countries and the impact of foreign and domestic events on the Foundation's overseas work. Administrative files also include communications issued from the New York office concerning international program policy.
Programs described in the field office administrative files include agricultural planning and management in Pakistan and India; rice and nutrition research in India and Indonesia; environmental studies, urban and regional studies and technical assistance support in Indonesia; and development planning and administration in Malaysia and Thailand. Education, population studies, and family planning were major focus areas for the Philippines, Malaysia, Pakistan, Bangladesh, India and Indonesia. In Indonesia, the Ford Foundation served a coordinating role in the public and private sector management of assistance activities from other agencies.
The administrative files for the Office for South and Southeast Asia (later Asia and the Pacific) describe changes in the administrative structure of the overseas program, including the creation of a regional Southeast Asia office in Bangkok, Thailand. The shift of administrative control from the regional offices in the Philippines and Malaysia was due to a concern that these offices would make programming decisions privileging the country in which they were located to the detriment of other countries under their regional jurisdiction. In addition, concerns about the adverse effect that a decline in the number of grants awarded and a reduction of overseas and New York staff might have on programming strategies on a global level are documented. Substantive correspondence and memoranda relating to then-current programs and new program development in Asia can also be found within the administrative files.
Another rich source of information are the budgets reports, also referred to as "program management costs." They contain general histories of regions and countries and descriptions of the Foundation's work abroad, as well as programming plans and projections. Many of the budgets include reviews of the political, social, and economic climate of the country in which the field office was located in order to inform the New York office of issues that could affect Foundation work. During the 1970s, for example, several offices were affected by changes in local governments. Martial law was instituted in the Philippines and there was an outbreak of civil unrest in Pakistan. Questions were raised regarding the safety of staff members and the effectiveness of grants during the uncertain political climate. As a result, programs were delayed and then reduced in Pakistan.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Administrative Files, 1960-1983; I; 8.08 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Regional and field offices documented in the collection include Dacca, Bangladesh (formerly East Pakistan); New Delhi, India; Jakarta, Indonesia; Islamabad, Pakistan; Bangkok, Thailand; and Manila, Philippines under the regional office for South and South East Asia (later Asia and the Pacific) and the Andean Region and Southern Cone, Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, and Nicaragua under the regional office for Latin America and the Caribbean. Also included are administrative files originating from the overarching International Division office at the Ford Foundation headquarters in New York. Files originating from the International Division office or for which the originating field office could not be determined were filed under the folder heading "General."
  The bulk of the series consists of memoranda between staff of the various field offices and the Foundation's New York office. Reports, charts and statistics, clippings and other attachments accompanying memoranda have been retained and kept together. Subjects discussed in memoranda include program planning and review, policy, and the possible impact of local political events on the Foundation's work, particularly in Pakistan, East Pakistan and the People's Republic of Bangladesh. Some files contain copies of correspondence to foreign government officials concerning the establishment of field offices in their respective countries and major Foundation staff changes.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by country or region in which the field offices are located.
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Memoranda Re: Budget and Program Planning, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Memoranda Re: Program Planning in Manila, Bangkok, Malaysia, 1973 September 26-December 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Asia and the Pacific -- Memoranda Re: Budget and Program Planning, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bangladesh Field Office -- Memoranda and Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bangladesh Field Office -- Memoranda, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bangladesh Field Office -- Memoranda, 1980-1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General -- Budget and Program Planning -- Report and Recommendations on Support Budgets and Other Supporting Projects of the International Division, 1967 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General -- Budget and Program Planning -- Progress Reports on Retrenchment of Management Costs, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General -- Health and Nutrition -- Memoranda, 1980 September 18-October 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General -- Office Administration -- DAP, Policy Study, Program Review, Communication Memoranda, 1980 September-1981 February (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General -- Program Review Meeting for Andean Region and Southern Cone -- Discussion Outline, Program Commitments, 1980 August 7-November 6 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - General -- Program Review Meetings for Bangladesh and Indonesia -- Discussion Outline, Background, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - General -- Program Review Meetings for India, Asia and Southeast Asia -- Discussion Outline, Background, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1964-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda and Draft Discussion Paper on Sri Lanka, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - India Field Office -- Program Assignments, Management Review Report, Report on Family Composition on Post, 1975-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda Re: Budget and Financial Status Reports, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - India Field Office -- Memoranda to New York Office, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Indonesia Field Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1978 Internal Policy, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Indonesia Field Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1979 Audits, Internal HR Policies, 1978 October-1980 July (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Indonesia Field Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1981 Closing of Manila and Bangkok Offices, DAPs, 1980 October-1982 August (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Indonesia Field Office -- Chronological Correspondence, Memoranda on Human Rights in Southeast Asia, 1974-1976 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Indonesia Field Office -- Chronological Correspondence, Memoranda Re: Corruption in Indonesia, 1976-1977 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: Policy, Discussion Papers, Foundation Reorganization, Wives Orientation in Pakistan, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1970-1974 Internal Policy Debates, Affirmative Action, Trip Reports (1 of 2), 1969-1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1970-1974 Internal Policy Debates, Affirmative Action, Trip Reports (2 of 2) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1975-1976 Ford Foundation Layoffs, Policy, Meeting Minutes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1976-1977 Meeting Reports, DAP, Policy (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1978 Internal Policy, Transit Strike, Human Rights in Indonesia, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1979 DAPs, Internal Policy, President McGeorge Bundy Retirement and Replacement by Franklin Thomas, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York Office -- Memoranda Re: FY 1981-1983, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Andean Region and Southern Cone -- Dye, Richard W. Memoranda (1 of 2), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Andean Region and Southern Cone -- Dye, Richard W. Memoranda (2 of 2), 1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Andean Region and Southern Cone -- Fellowships/Small Program Actions -- Correspondence and Memoranda, 1980 September-1981 March (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Andean Region and Southern Cone -- Memoranda Re: Budget and Office Closing, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Argentina -- Request for Grant Action, Memoranda Re: Grantee Arrest, 1980 November 5-1981 March 4 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Bolivia -- Memoranda Re: Policy on Bolivian Refugee Cases, 1980 October 20 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Brazil -- Gardner, James A. -- Memoranda Re: Foundation-Grantee Relationship, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Chile -- Memoranda Re: Evaluations and Affirmative Action, 1980 October-1981 March (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Colombia and Venezuela -- Memoranda Re: DAPs, 1980 October-November (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Forward Planning -- Memoranda Re: Budget Projections and Program Reviews, 1973-1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Memoranda Re: Review of Agricultural Centers and Meeting on Social Science Development, Clipping, 1980 November-1981 March (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Nicaragua -- Human Rights, 1978 January 2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Office for Latin America and the Caribbean -- Schuman, Barry Memoranda, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Office for Southeast Asia -- Program Status and Annual Reports, 1969-1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Office for Southeast Asia -- Reports of Kuala Lampur, Malaysia Office, 1963-1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Office for Southeast Asia -- Reports on Status of Grants and Projects, Budget Projections of Bangkok, Thailand Office, 1968-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Office for Southeast Asia -- Briefing Papers and Drafts, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Office for Southeast Asia -- Reports of/from Bangkok, Thailand Office, 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Pakistan Field Office -- Memoranda Re: Political Situation, 1964-1969 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Pakistan Field Office -- Memoranda Re: Budget, 1974-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Thailand Field Office -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Administrative Documents, 1962-1969 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Thailand Field Office -- Memoranda, 1970-1972 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Thailand Field Office -- Memoranda, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Thailand Field Office -- Memoranda, Attached Reports and Documents, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Thailand Field Office -- Memoranda, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Budgets, 1967-1974; II; 3.94 Cubic Feet
  This series consists of budget reports for Fiscal Years 1967/69 through 1974/75. The Foundation Fiscal Year ran from October 1 to September 30 and budget planning occurred the year prior. The field offices submitting budgets include Bangkok, Thailand; Jakarta, Indonesia; Manila, Philippines; New Delhi, India; Islamabad, Pakistan; and Bangladesh. Several of the budgets for 1972 contain responses to a request from Foundation President McGeorge Bundy to submit ideas for new initiatives and program directions.
  The budgets contain general histories of the region or country, descriptions of Foundation work, and program plans and projections. They include information about annual goals, rationales for continued funding or additional funding, and proposals for new initiatives. The budgets also document modifications in programming based on new initiatives or extended support over time. For example, in Bangladesh, after ten years of support for program initiatives on population studies, the Foundation's focus shifted to issues of health and increasing support for women's issues.
  - FY 1967-1969 -- Office for South and Southeast Asia Administrative Budgets (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - FY 1969 -- International Division, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - FY 1970 -- Proposed Budget, Management Costs, 1969 June (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - FY 1970 -- Asia and the Pacific General Statement, Charts, New Delhi, Islamabad (1 of 3), 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - FY 1970 -- Bangkok, Jakarta, Manila, East Asia, Resource Base (2 of 3), 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - FY 1970 -- New York (3 of 3), 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - FY 1971 -- Asia and the Pacific General Statement, New Delhi, Islamabad, Bangkok, Jakarta, Manila, East Asia, Resource Base, Management Costs (1 of 2), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - FY 1971 -- Management Costs (cont.), New York, Manpower Projections for India, Indonesia, Pakistan, Philippines, and Thailand, Resource Base, East Asia (2 of 2), 1970 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - FY 1972 -- Asia and the Pacific Program Budget -- Management Costs, Charts, New Delhi, Islamabad, Bangkok, Jakarta, Manila, New York, Staff List, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - FY 1973 -- Asia and the Pacific General Statement, Charts, Staff List, New Delhi, Islamabad, Bangladesh, Bangkok, Manila, Jakarta, Resource Base, New York, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - FY 1974 -- Bangladesh, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - FY 1974 -- India, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - FY 1974 -- Indonesia, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - FY 1974 -- Pakistan, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - FY 1974 -- Regional (Philippines, Thailand, Malaysia), 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - FY 1974-1975, 1972-1974 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Consultants, 1975-1981; III; 1.31 Cubic Feet
  Separated Materials
  Cross reference forms have been placed in folders where reports have been removed from files and relocated to the Archives' collection of scanned staff and consultant reports. A list of these reports can be found in Appendix A.
  This series contains correspondence and memoranda between program staff members and consultants as well as reports on trips by consultants.
  - Cornelius, Wayne -- Memoranda on Research Project, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Fagan, Richard -- Narrative Report, Correspondence, Reports (separated), 1976-1978 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Fishlow, Albert -- Reports (separated), 1979 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Froman, Josephine -- Evaluation Report (separated), 1980 April 6 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Goodman, Louis -- Memoranda, Reports (separated), 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Havens, A. Eugene -- Memoranda, Reports (separated), 1975-1978 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Mertens, Walter -- Reports (separated), 1979 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Writings, 1975-1976; IV; 1.31 Cubic Feet
  This series consists of two articles written and proposed for submission by Carl J. Green, the Ford Foundation Representative in Japan. The articles are "The United States and Japan – Improving the Dialogue" (1975) and "Mr. Carter, South Korea and Japan" (1977).
  - "The United States and Japan: Improving the Dialogue," Proposed Submission for Publication, Carl J. Green, 1975 April 22 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "Mr. Carter, South Korea, and Japan," Op-Ed Submission, New York Times, Carl J. Green, 1976 December 22 (Box 8, Folder 16)